<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Machine Learning | Riccardo Rubini</title><link>https://riccardorubini98.github.io/tag/machine-learning/</link><atom:link href="https://riccardorubini98.github.io/tag/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Machine Learning</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://riccardorubini98.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Machine Learning</title><link>https://riccardorubini98.github.io/tag/machine-learning/</link></image><item><title>Reviews analysis and processing</title><link>https://riccardorubini98.github.io/project/amazon-book-review/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://riccardorubini98.github.io/project/amazon-book-review/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this project, we conducted two common tasks in text mining using a large collection of e-book reviews from Amazon.com. Our main objectives were as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Text Classification for Sentiment Analysis:&lt;/strong> Our first goal was to automatically determine the sentiment expressed in the reviews, whether they were positive or negative. To accomplish this, we employed a supervised technique known as Text Classification. After experimenting with various methods, we found that the lasso logistic classifier provided the most satisfactory results. It achieved a recall rate of 92% for positive reviews and 90% for negative reviews. In simpler terms, this means that our model was able to accurately identify whether a review was positive or negative in the majority of cases.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Topic Modeling:&lt;/strong> The second objective of our project was to uncover the main topics discussed in the e-book reviews. We used an unsupervised technique called Topic Modeling for this purpose. Imagine it as a method to identify the key themes or subjects that frequently came up in the reviews. After trying different approaches, we discovered that the algebraic Non-negative Matrix Factorization (NMF) technique was the most effective in identifying reliable topics. These topics were related to various aspects, such as different shades of opinions and various categories of books that were being reviewed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In summary, our project involved analyzing a large number of e-book reviews from Amazon.com. We used machine learning techniques to determine whether the reviews were positive or negative (sentiment analysis) and to identify the main topics that emerged from these reviews (topic modeling). The results of our efforts showed that our models were quite accurate in sentiment analysis, and we were able to extract meaningful topics from the reviews using advanced mathematical techniques like NMF.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Time series analysis</title><link>https://riccardorubini98.github.io/project/timeseries/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://riccardorubini98.github.io/project/timeseries/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this project, we conducted an analysis and forecasting of carbon monoxide (CO) emissions using a combination of statistical and deep learning techniques. We explored various modeling approaches, including AutoRegressive Integrated Moving Average (ARIMA) models, Unobserved Components Model (UCM), and Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) deep neural networks, to select the most suitable model. Our final selected model achieved a Mean Absolute Percentage Error (MAPE) of 12%, demonstrating its accuracy in predicting CO emissions&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Digital Marketing</title><link>https://riccardorubini98.github.io/project/webmarketing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://riccardorubini98.github.io/project/webmarketing/</guid><description>&lt;p>The primary goal of this project is to better understand and manage customer churn (when customers stop using our services) and to explore the potential impact of mail marketing in reducing churn rates.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Project Components:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Anti-Churn Model:&lt;/strong>
We will build a specialized model known as an &amp;ldquo;anti-churn model.&amp;rdquo; This model helps us predict the likelihood of each customer leaving our company&amp;rsquo;s services. By analyzing various factors, such as customer behavior and engagement, we can estimate the probability that a customer might stop using our products or services.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>RFM Segmentation:&lt;/strong>
In addition to the anti-churn model, we will use a technique called &amp;ldquo;RFM segmentation.&amp;rdquo; RFM stands for Recency, Frequency, and Monetary value. This segmentation method helps us identify our most valuable customers based on how recently they made a purchase, how often they do so, and how much money they spend. Understanding these high-value customers is crucial for targeted marketing efforts.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Mail Marketing Analysis:&lt;/strong>
We will also investigate the effectiveness of mail marketing campaigns in reducing customer churn rates. This involves sending promotional materials or offers to customers via physical mail. We will analyze whether these mail marketing efforts have a positive impact on retaining customers and if they can help decrease churn.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Project Benefits:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Improved Customer Retention:&lt;/strong> By identifying customers at risk of leaving and high-value customers, we can implement strategies to keep valuable clients and reduce churn. Our strategy provides a 20% increase in performance over the classical approach
&lt;strong>Cost-Efficient Marketing:&lt;/strong> The analysis of mail marketing effectiveness will help us determine whether this traditional marketing approach is worth the investment in retaining customers.
&lt;strong>Data-Driven Decisions:&lt;/strong> The project will rely on data analysis to make informed decisions, ensuring our marketing efforts are targeted and efficient.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>